# Eric Lachenmeier

Palo Alto, CA 94301 (650) 283-8835 eric.lachenmeier@gmail.com

http://ericlachenmeier.herokuapp.com/ www.linkedin.com/in/ericlachenmeier

### **SUMMARY**

Senior design engineer and entrepreneur. Coding skills include Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, HTML, & CSS. Product design skills using SolidWorks, AutoCAD, and FEA. Other skills include financial modeling, ISO certification, and project management. Software/IT knowledge includes Adobe CS, ERP, CRM, SQL, CPM, DBs and Quick Books. Product design experience includes scientific instrumentation, optics, semiconductor processing equipment, software and services.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Consulting: Product Development, Finance, Engineering, Strategic Planning, RoR dev, Investing

Palo Alto, CA 2009 to present

**COMPLETE GENOMICS INC.** DNA sequencing service, acquired by BGI *Vice President, Corporate Development* 

Mt. View, CA 2006 to 2009

- Developed a service-based business model based on a 2<sup>nd</sup> generation DNA sequencing technology
- Led the search for a corporate headquarters and managed the build-out and move to the new facility
- Co-authored a NIST grant proposal that resulted in winning a 5 year, \$12M federally funded grant. Hired and managed a 12 person development team.
- Negotiated and closed million dollar service contracts with major Pharma, Biotech, and Research organizations.

ALLEGRO BIOSCIENCES, Internet-based genome research, virtual laboratory and data management San Diego, CA Founder 2000 to 2002

- Developed and launched a web-based research tool to design and conduct experiments on the web
- · Developed software architecture, managed software team, and recruited a network of service providers
- Led sales and marketing activities
- Led investor road shows in Europe and the US, raised seed round of financing,
- Negotiated a Series A term sheet
- Authored and filed patents

**INCYTE GENOMICS,** A pioneer in genetic research, now Incyte Corporation, publicly traded as INCY *Vice President, Technology Development* 

Palo Alto, CA 1996 to 2000

- · Led the development of numerous laboratory robotic systems, fixtures and labor and time saving tools
- Designed and deployed two generations of DNA sequencing platforms
- · Created the firms first engineering department
- Built and led a world-class, cross-functional technology development team consisting of biologists, software and mechanical engineers, and chemists

Eric Lachenmeier Page 2

**LYNX THERAPEUTICS,** Genetic mRNA expression service, merged with Solexa, acquired by Illumina *Founding Engineer* 

Hayward, CA 1995 to 1996

 Design engineer and molecular biologist, designing optical imaging systems, fluorescence detection instruments, and conducting molecular validation experiments

**APPLIED BIOSYSTEMS**, DNA Analysis Systems: PCR, DNA sequencing and synthesis *Design Engineer* 

Foster City, CA 1988 to 1995

- Project Leader and Inventor, ABI 310 DNA Analyzer, a system that has created revenues exceeding \$400M
- Recruited and managed a high-performance team of chemists and engineers.
- Inventions included optics, Peltier cooled CCD, separation gels, electro kinetic DNA stacking technology, and the control & analysis software
- Oversaw the overall instrument design including software and hardware details and documentation

# **Inventor ABI 377 DNA Sequencer**

Inventor of a major DNA analysis platform used to sequence the Human Genome (Patent 5,543,026 August 1996). Generated revenues in excess of \$400 million

**BECKMAN INSTRUMENTS** 

Palo Alto, CA

Design Engineer: Biomek 1000 - laboratory robotics & liquid handling

1986 to 1988

HEWLETT PACKARD

Palo Alto, CA

Production Engineer: Microwave production engineer, process improvement engineer (SQC, JIT)

1984 to 1986

#### **EDUCATION**

THE WHARTON SCHOOL, UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA Master of Business Administration, Finance Major

Philadelphia, PA 2004

MASSACHUSSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering

Cambridge, MA 1984

# PROFESSIONAL RECOGNITIONS and INTERESTS

- Volunteer for the CASA foster child program 2012
- Session chairman and frequent participant at biotechnology and investment conferences
- Stanford University Office of Technology Licensing, 2001: Out-licensing Advisor for University gene portfolio
- Human Genome research grant reviewer, 1998, U.S. Department of Energy, Washington DC
- Multiple patents in the areas of DNA analysis and engineered devices
- Designed and built 2 custom houses: architect, general contractor, electrician, and plumber